<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-05T17:26:12+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Heirtomb Redux</title><subtitle>Documenting the redevelopment of our jam game, Heirtomb. New title pending!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Game States</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/2020/08/03/game-states.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game States" /><published>2020-08-03T17:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-03T17:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/2020/08/03/game-states</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/2020/08/03/game-states.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m an infrastructure nerd at heart. I just love getting stuck into some abstract system that has very little reference to the material world. It’s the niche that I’ve found at work in my day job, and it’s what I decided to start with here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s be clear, I didn’t start with this kind of stuff &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; because it’s my favourite! I also did it because it’s something that in the past, we’ve tended to forget, and push back, and neglect until suddenly it’s a massive problem and necessitates lots of awkward changes to account for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the jam, we started by implementing the basic game mechanics: the world grid, the entities, the player moving around the world, etc. This was all fine until towards the end of the time, when we realised that “uh-oh! If you get a game over you need to restart! And we don’t have any easy way to do that!” So it all ended up being rushed, desperately trying to make sure that everything got deleted and recreated, so nothing was hanging over from your last attempt. Well, we’re not having that this time, because I’m implementing the game state machine &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the jargon. What do I mean by “game state machine”? Well, a “state machine” is a computer science term that refers to a sort of abstract “machine” that can transition between various “states”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Look mom, I’m using my degree!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can imagine it a bit like a flow chart. Actually, it’s exactly like a flow chart. Why didn’t my lecturers just describe it like a flow chart? Lousy, good for nothing degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re still not sure what I’m on about, this is best explained with an example. Let me show you what I was aiming for for this particular game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/HeirtombRedux/assets/images/initial_game_state_machine.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;/HeirtombRedux/assets/images/initial_game_state_machine.png&quot; alt=&quot;A flowchart with labeled arrows between labeled boxes&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the boxes represent “states” that our game can be in, and the arrows represent how you transition between those states, with the labels describing the action. So to move between the “Playing the game” state and the “Pause Menu” state, the player has to “Pause”, and to move back, the player has to “Unpause”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Start” state just tells you where to start reading from. A few things to note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are plenty of loops in this flowchart! This is by design, players can go round and round these states as much as they need. They can pause and unpause as often as they like, fail and start over to their hearts’ content.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most state machines (especially those used for pattern matching etc) will have an “output” or “final” state. We don’t need that here, since players can just quit the game at any time, and there’s no point linking every single state to some extra “Game Closed” state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The transition between “Start” and “Main Menu” has no label. This is just to show that there’s no specific action the player needs to take to get to the Main Menu, they just click on the icon and they’re straight in.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is pretty general! Given how much trouble we’ve had with this in the past, this may be a candidate for some utility code that we can just reuse whenever we start a new project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with all these kinds of things, I’m not instructing you on how you &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be doing this sort of thing, just explaining how I’m choosing to do it, and hopefully explaining why it made sense to me. Leave a comment if you have a better suggestion. That was a joke, there’s no comment section on this thing. Not yet anyway… Hey, you can always tweet at me if you have a burning desire to tell me I’m an idiot. I’m sure I’d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But geneuinely, if you want to see more detail, see some actual code, or want me to change anything about how I’m doing these, please do let me know! Links to social things are at the bottom of every page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m an infrastructure nerd at heart. I just love getting stuck into some abstract system that has very little reference to the material world. It’s the niche that I’ve found at work in my day job, and it’s what I decided to start with here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Beginnings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/first_post" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Beginnings" /><published>2020-08-02T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/new-beginnings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/HeirtombRedux/first_post">&lt;p&gt;“Why are we starting again”, you ask? Well let me tell you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re in a game jam, there’s often very little time to plan, and very little time to actually write the code. All around, just not a lot of time to work with. This means three things,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are planning with the short timescale in mind, which may mean you have to leave out or simplify interesting stuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The plans you make may not be as well thought out as they could be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The code will probably end up being quite messy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these are reasons why now, with the pressure off, we want to start from scratch. We have the time to do whatever we want now, which means we don’t have to simplify things. We don’t have to make sure that everything we want to do can be done in 48 hours! Also, we have the time to really properly design this game. Last time, we added enemies because they were the first thing we could think of that might threaten the tree that the player needs to protect. But do they actually support the theme that we’re aiming for? For that matter, is having the player protecting a tree the best expression of our theme to begin with? We’ve now had the time to think really intensely about what we want to do, and we’re trying to throw out all the assumptions that we made in order to get to the core of what we want to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, we have the time to make sure the code is better. As the deadline of a jam gets closer, you tend to have less and less time to care about whether you’re implementing things in the best way. What does this mean in practice? When we’re writing code, we generally try to make sure that it has certain useful properties. Some examples of ideals we try to aim for are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code should be easily understandable
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is often said that a programmer’s time is mostly spent reading code rather than writing it. This means that code that is hard to read can waste a lot of time. Equally, making sure that the code you right now will make sense in six months takes time too. But as they say, “a stitch in time saves nine”, and “an ounce of prevention is better than a pound of cure”! It is generally better to save time in the future, rather than now&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code should be flexible
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Above I said that programmers read more code than they write, well it’s equally true that programmers probably spend more time rewriting old code than writing new code! With that in mind, we should try to make code as easy to change as possible. There are many different strategies designed with this in mind, and different ones are more appropriate in different situations. Most, if not all, of them require time spent planning them and then time spent implementing them to make sure that they are effective&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the code that we ended up writing during the jam was neither easy to understand, nor particularly flexible. We intend to use whatever parts of the original code we can salvage, but on the whole we’ll be taking the lessons we learned during the jam, and simply doing it better this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, any changes to the design will also require new or different code, so we may not even be able to reuse all the good bits. So which parts of the design have we actually changed? Well, I don’t want to spoil too many details of the experience we’re aiming for, since a lot of it will be about interpreting what’s in front of you as it happens. Rest assured I’ll expand on details as and when I need to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really looking forward to getting to work on this again, and also to be writing this dev log! This is the first time I’ve tried anything like this in earnest, so this will be something of a learning process for me too. Hopefully Max will be able to chip in occasionally with updates from his side of the process too. I hope you enjoy what we have to offer!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Why are we starting again”, you ask? Well let me tell you.</summary></entry></feed>